unlike many other cells of your body
your muscle cells have a remarkable
ability to adapt to stimulus and insult
other cells will often just die when
triggered to one great example is our
immune cells however muscle cells don't
have that luxury because we don't
generally produce more muscle cells
after we mature and one of the
remarkable aspects of muscle is how
resilient they are to aging with the
most remarkable effects being in their
memory and that specifically ties into
stem cells that are linked to your
musculature so let's explain what that
all means from a scientific standpoint
but also what it means for you first off
I'm going to show you some fascinating
information gleaned from this study the
researchers of this study offer more on
the role of a particular type of stem
cell known as satellite cell has on
making muscle resilient to things like
disuse in brief satellite cells are also
closely related to the lineage of stem
cells called mesenchimal stem cells
these cells have some of the flexibility
of stem cells but are destined to become
a limited number of cells like muscle
cells now I did mention that we don't
typically develop more muscle cells
later in life and that's still true but
satellite cells support muscle cells in
a unique way that we'll get into for now
just just know that satellite cells are
like stem cells and they sit on top of
the muscle cells now what did these
researchers do exactly they recruited
men and women to perform a resistance
training program on one arm and nothing
on the other this is called a unilateral
experiment they trained that one arm for
10 weeks then they detrained meaning
that they did not lift weights for 16
weeks they then trained both arms for an
additional 10 weeks if you're confused
why they would do that you'll understand
shortly if we look at the data we're
looking at the overall arm size the top
three graphs are for the initially
trained arm and the bottom three graphs
are for the control arm the one that was
not initially trained the individual
dots and dotted lines are the muscle
thickness measurements for each
participant the reason for the dotted
line is to relate each dot to the same
person at the end of that measurement
period so you can track how they did
individually for example in the top left
we see that everyone increased their
muscle mass from resistance training
this is confirmed by the asterisk
indicating a statistically significant
effect on the other hand one look to the
right during the draining phase these
same people lost muscle mass which
obviously makes sense you use it or you
you lose it then for both arms when
training they both gained muscle I'm
probably not really blowing your mind
here but I'm establishing that the
researchers indicate that the training
works and the instruments used are
sensitive to changes this is important
next the researchers also measured the
amount of myonuclei present what is that
well your muscle cells have multiple
nucleuses or
nuclei these are the areas of your cell
that contain the vast majority of your
DNA your genes since these are the
warehouses that house your genetic
information they're also the starting
place for the production of proteins
like those necessary for muscle growth
if you have more of them you might be
able to produce protein more quickly so
keep that very important point in mind
because this is where the stem cells the
satellite cells will come in it's also
why the researchers used such an odd
study design okay the researchers
Quantified the number of nuclei in the
muscle cells of the people before and
after training these data are only from
the trained arm the left side is the
initial training the middle is the
draining period and the far right is the
retraining phase interestingly we see
that the muscle cells are generating new
nuclei during both training phases but
no change in in the draining phase but
are they actually generating new nuclei
no not really in reality this is where
the satellite cells come into play you
see as you stimulate your muscle
satellite cells will also be activated
through numerous mechanisms that we
really don't have time for and when
activated we'll literally fuse with the
mature muscle cells in doing so they
donate their nuclei allowing the muscle
cell to now contain more nuclei an
assumed Advantage but is it well if we
look at the measure called myonuclear
domain that Story begins to unfold
bionuclear domain is merely the amount
of total cell that is controlled by a
single nucleus think about it like
having one warehouse for x amount of
square kilom miles the more warehouses
around the less area each Warehouse has
to supply so if you have more nuclear I
AKA warehouses the myonuclear domain
will shrink as they can concentrate on
covering less cell space looking at that
data the left side is the trained arm
the right side is the control arm we can
see that in the type two muscle cells a
particular type of muscle cell the
trained arm has more myonuclei
integrated indicating by the average
line in Black being slanted upwards to
the left relative to the right side
however this is also statistically
confirmed by the asterisk there so let's
pause here and think about what we know
so far so one we know that resistance
training increases muscle size two we
know that stopping resistance training
reduces muscle size but does not reduce
the number of nuclei in the muscle cells
three we now suspect that the number of
nuclei in increased initially and
remains through the detraining then
increases again upon retraining leading
to a permanent effect on the myonuclear
domain of your musculature we can
speculate that because if we look at the
draining data here's the muscle size and
here's the myonuclear amount we can
clearly see that the trained arm lost
muscle size yet the number of myonuclei
remain stable in addition if you look at
the vertical axis the muscle sizes were
about the same after the draining period
for both arms and since the number of
myonuclei increas during the training
phase it is reasonable to assume that
although the muscle size is similar the
latent potential for muscle growth is
still greater in the previously trained
arm why do I say that well if we look at
the relationship between myonuclear
domain and the muscle growth we see an
inverse relationship that means that as
my nuclear domain shrinks that's the
same as more nuclei the change in muscle
size increases the vertical axis is the
muscle cross-section the muscle size the
horizontal axis is the increasing
myonuclear domain as the myonuclear
domain increases the relationship
indicates A reduced muscle size as the
line approaches zero there in simple
terms the more nuclei you have in your
muscle cells the better relationship to
muscle growth but there are some caveats
that we should get into before we do
we've been discussing the increase in
myonuclei those muscle stem cells
integrating and donating their nuclei to
the muscle cells but there's more
information on other cells that are also
affected by a similar process in
addition the researchers touch on some
genetic changes that occur since it's
too much for me to cover here I have an
extended version of this video that is
available to the physionic Insiders if
you're interested along with my full
catalog of work be sure to check it out
it's in the description box I'll see you
over there okay the caveats one that
last datm that I showed you was only a
relationship an
association when they measured the
direct impact they did not measure a
statistically significant effect now in
numerical terms the trained muscle grew
about 30% and the control muscle after
its training in the second training
period grew 14% that's 15 16% difference
was not statistically significant
between the two conditions although
there was a statistically significant
increase when just comparing the trained
muscle before and after which all might
mean that they didn't have enough data
to detect a difference comparing the two
but that's pure speculation the
researchers also mentioned that one
participant had Wild results and
although they didn't exclude that data
from the analysis they did check if it
had an outsized effect on the results
and they found that it did when removing
that one outlier the results were now
different between the two groups meaning
that the arm with the more myonuclei did
grow more muscle although it started at
a similar
Baseline one more thing before I
simplify all this for you and offer some
takeaways the researchers acknowledge
that not all the studies indicate a
preservation of myonuclei from dra
trining some studies indicate there is a
reduction going against this idea that
these satellite cells remain
forever however that data also suffers
from some insensitivity in how the
experiments were performed for example
this study that we just went over
separated out the myonuclei from other
nuclei increasing the sensitivity and
accuracy of the measurements this was
not done in other studies so where does
that leave us well according to the
current study it tells us a few things
one it suggests although I'd like to see
more evidence of this to be certain
that's stimulating your musculature
through training increases the
acquisition of these muscle related stem
cells called satellite cells as they
fuse into the muscle cell in addition
these satellite cells fuse and remain
for months even when the muscle is no
longer being stimulated other Research
indicates that this is a permanent
effect leading to this ageless effect of
satellite Cells Two functionally this
all means that one of the major reasons
that you can regain muscle and grow
muscle much more quickly if you've
gained it once before is because of this
seemingly permanent effect on your
muscle cells by satellite cells and
three the real world application is the
same as any other you should try lifting
weights at least once per week and
preferably more to create this permanent
ageless mark on your musculature in
addition if you get injured or can't
maintain that exercise for long
stretches of time don't worry because
yes your muscle mass will decrease but
your imprinted satellite cell infus
muscles will regain at a supercharged
rate and set you up for further muscle
growth grow in the future how freaking
cool is that I mean
seriously anyway I can also explain some
of the best practices for muscle growth
right here and I'll speak with you over
there thanks for tuning in